Inventory of the Clara L. Lawrence Papers 1763-1939
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Clara L. Lawrence Papers 1763, 1883-1888, 1909-1939
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2009.299
1.60
Lawrence, Clara L. arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center from Sharon L. Zuber on 07/14/2009.
Accruals
Acquisition information for material received after 7/13/2009 is available by consulting a Special Collections Research Center staff member.
Biographical Note
Clara Louise Walde Lawrence was a nurse in the period before, during, and after World War I. Her family lived in Rochester, New York and her two children were named Betty and Donald. Further information about this individual or organization may be available in the Special Collections Research Center Wiki: http://scrc.swem.wm.edu/wiki/index.php/Clara L. Lawrence.
Scope and Contents
This collection primarily concerns Clara Louise Walde Lawrence's career as a nurse in the period before, during, and after World War I. Materials in the collection include correspondence, scrapbooks, diaries, photographs and negatives, pamphlets, medical supplies, and other publications. Most of the correspondence, photographs, and publications relate to either WWI or nursing. Notable correspondents include a letter from Julia Cherney (Bateman) to Clara Walde while serving as a missionary in China. Other items of interest include a 1763 Boston Gazette as well as several 19th century American newspapers. The collection also includes Lawrence's Veterans Administration account books from the 1930s. Transcriptions were created of the correspondence before the collection was donated to the Special Collections Research Center and are available here as PDFs. Acc. 2010.784 contains correspondence, 1909-1923, primarily
Additional Information
Related Materials
A compact disc with digital copies of transcripts of letters was pulled from this collection and was added to the Manuscripts Audiovisual Collection in November 2010.
Separated Materials
A compact disc filled with digital copies of transcripts of letters was pulled from this collection and was added to the Manuscripts Audiovisual Collection in November 2010.
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Diaries; Letters (correspondence); Negatives; Photographs; Scrapbooks
Topical Term:
Nurses--1910-1920; Women--Travel.; World War, 1914-1918--Medical and sanitary affairs.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Correspondence, 1909-1937; id60419
  - id60824 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, Binder 1, 1909-1920, id60420 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Binder 2, 1917-1919; id60421 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Binder 3, Part 1, 1918; id60825 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, Binder 3, Part 2, 1918; id60423 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Binder 3, Part 3, 1919; id60424 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, Binder 3, Part 4, 1919; id60425 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Greeting Cards, 1928-1937; id65215 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Biographical Material, 1910-1939; id64694
  - id60827 (Box 1)
    - Photo Album, 1916-1920; id64696 (Box 1)
  - id60829 (Box 2)
    - Souvenir Book, 1911-1920; id64697 (Box 2)
  - id60835 (Box 4)
    - Registered Nurse Certificates from the States of Michigan and New York, 1915, 1923; id60836 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Red Cross Publication, Prayer Book, and Nurses Calendar, 1913-1918; id60837 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Veterans Bureau Fiduciary Account Books, 1931-1939; id60838 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Journal, 1918-1919; id60841 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Camp McLellan Photographs, 1917; id60840 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Negatives of Family Pictures, undated; id60839 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Artifacts to be rehoused, 1910-1939; id60826 (Box 6)
- Publications, 1763-1939; id64695
  - id60422 (Box 5)
    - Maps and Brochures, 1918; id60426 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper clippings and Documents, 1763, 1883-1888, 1914-1938; id60427 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Nursing Pamphlets, 1914, 1939; id60428 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Base 19 History, 1917-1918; id60843 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Language Books, 1913-1917; id60844 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Pamphlets, 1862-1928; id60845 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Acc. 2010.784: Letters, 1909-1923; id82180